Frontier models are overused, We throw all kinds of trivial problems
at them all the time.
we should not do that. It's a waste of compute.
It's a waste of money. It's a waste of tokens.
It's a waste of water.
Good evening.
So, yeah,
just briefly introduce myself.
I'm Sean Smith.
I work on MCP
agents and various open source projects and initiatives that are hugging face.
A couple of things I do there is I look after our MCP server,
make sure that that's healthy and running well.
I help maintain our skills projects.
And I also was a very,
very early adopter of MCP and currently in MCP maintainer and community moderator
I spent most of my time at the moment
working on transports, so if anyone wants to talk MCP transports
during the networking, that's an reasonable topic.
I'm hoping that most people here
are familiar with hugging face in one way or another.
Some few nods. Yep.
So we're, we've got a huge community
and we host models.
We host research papers and data sets to help people use models.
We also have thousands and thousands of AI applications hosted on our spaces
platform, so people can develop and build and train models, and then they can show
demos or host those things on our on our zero GPU services.
And it's all very, very good fun.
So I mentioned I was an MCP maintainer and a fairly early adopter.
And so for this talk, what I was going to do was sort of
go through some of the stuff
we've been doing with skills, but really kind of start off
with kind of thinking back to where we started with tool calling
and how we've ended up with skills and how we've then ended up with
some of these more complex evaluation pipelines and tools.
And so if we kind of go back to when MCP was first launched,
the it was all actually really, really quite straightforward.
If you recall, if you were playing with this stuff, then
you would connect an MCP server to your LM.
You would normally have to configure that with a JSON file,
and you would write a prompt and you would see the tool cool.
And you would kind of clap and say, well, that's you know, that's brilliant.
I've connected one thing to another.
Things that we didn't really have then were we
didn't really have sort of particularly good harnesses.
You know, we had the Claude desktop app and we had a few other kind of fairly
custom, custom applications that we could play with, but nothing
that was kind of really nice to use or easy to configure.
We didn't have agents ND files.
I mean, that feels quite straightforward, doesn't it?
Such a simple thing is,
you know, a text file which helps drive our agents behavior.
But we hadn't kind of agreed that that was actually a reasonable
and a good thing to do and share between our tools.
And the other thing that kind of changed was
we didn't have long running tool loops. So,
you know, it used to be the case.
You could kind of prompt it to change to all three tool calls together,
but actually these kind of loops that from a single prompt
will run for an hour or two hours and sort of change the 50 or 60 tool calls
as it goes, as it moves towards the task, just weren't really a thing.
Okay, so so what happened and what changed?
So the the kind of magic, if you like
is, is that labs knowing that particularly for coding tasks,
they could place models in environments and conduct reinforcement
learning on them.
And actually it's fairly
what you actually do is relatively straightforward conceptually, which is you
place your model in a harness in an environment,
and you write a reward function and you give it a task.
And typically the reward functions are fairly deterministic,
and you may be able to judge the task on a scale of sort of
0 to 10 or, or whatsoever.
And then you generate that data and you, you then train the model
to kind of reward itself and, and keep driving the loop
without needing lots and lots of intervention and steering.
Something that we've kind of added on hub is a bit smaller.
I was going to do is zoom in for this, but something that we've also added on
the hub is agent Environments to actually help set up
these kind of training environments
so that you can have a go at doing your own reinforcement learning.
It's quite a good fun if you the sort of the typical starting point for
this would be if you want to train a model
to play a game, or if you want to train a model
to do a couple of other things,
it's fairly straightforward to write the award functions for that,
and then place that in an environment and train a model to do so.
The the other kind of,
kind of quite important thing that's happened here, and I
look at this in just a second is how,
how free of the harnesses models have become.
And what I mean by that is that harnesses
can now be very, very simple to get to get jobs done.
And the example there is many SWE agent, which is a single
100 line Python function.
Effectively that can score 76 I think actually the latest numbers
are 78%, 78.6% on SWE bench.
So you have all of these very,
very complex harnesses, but actually a single 100 line program
can get close to the state of the art performance straight away.
And so this is something that we've kind of seen evolve over
the last over the last year is actually as our models
become more and more capable, inversely, our harnesses become an awful lot simpler.
And the kind of changes that we've seen is general purpose is
now were given direct shell access.
I've put an asterisk there
because actually sometimes we'll give them secure shell access
or through an environment like just bash or something, which is more secure.
But typically we give our we give our models
a way of kind of navigating freeform with the outside world.
We have much fewer hacks and tricks to keep models from doing.
Do we might occasionally inject something into the into the message loop,
but those kind of techniques are kind of a lot simpler.
If again,
if you were kind of developing LM applications about a year or so ago,
you would normally be looking through various libraries
and you'd be looking at the API surface and you'd be looking at the multiple.
You kind of be kind of figuring out,
how can I build a workflow out of these, out of these steps and considering it?
If you're building applications now, you do something completely different,
which is you.
You take any, any tool loop
that you can easily get hold of, and you can basically just start using it.
So it's again, a lot of this stuff, as I say,
these models become more and more capable of doing this stuff.
We have. We can have simpler and simpler harnesses.
Building these applications are simpler, and the kind of workflows that we may have
previously deterministically coded have kind of been taken over by models
simply being strong enough to follow instructions, or by models
generating their own scripts and code so that they can achieve a goal.
Okay. So these are these are the kind of things we see.
So this is also why skills are interesting.
Because it's quite easy to look at skills and almost dismiss them as being
well it's just a bunch of markdown files.
I mean, how simple can that be?
But there's something else that's actually that's actually going on here, right?
Which is that we talked to be self directing.
We give them a task.
We give them the capability to navigate
so they can look at content, and then they can ingest content.
And critically having ingested content they can
then act upon what they've just ingested. Okay.
So this effectively means that models can do very, very complex tasks.
And we can configure and set them up in very, very, very simple ways.
So given that just
this is just an example that I like,
one of the things that we, we like doing with our MCP server
and with our, with our spaces is we have, you know, as I've mentioned,
thousands of image generation models, OCR style models, audio generation.
You know, pretty much any custom models, privacy filters, most recently
to pretty much any custom model is available through either
an MCP API or a gradient API on our platform.
And what we've because models have just got this little bit of extra capability.
The way that used to work for us was that we would, in the MCP server
say, right, we'll use I want to use this particular model to generate an image,
or I want to use this particular model to conduct some OCR.
But what we can now do is dynamically give models access to
literally thousands of
capabilities with a 45 token tool footprint,
because the model can say, we can ask,
you know, I would like to rotate the image.
I would like to move between two frames.
I would like to generate an audio book from this web page.
And because the model is capable of calling a tool very simply,
which in this case is our Dynamic spaces tool, we then effectively have a gateway,
which means that we can access literally hundreds
and thousands of models through a very, very small token footprint.
Okay.
So it lets us mix and match and, you know, just have not just capabilities
to read skill files, but capabilities to actually conduct inference
against pretty much any model and discover those things at runtime
rather than having to set these things up earlier. Okay.
So so this is the kind of, you know, the kind of power
that RL and these things have opened up for us.
And of course, that's why this is opened up skills.
This is why skills are important.
Because the ability for the model to navigate.
By that I mean, you know, list files or groups and skills
in a very, very token dense format.
So it doesn't matter that we're using shell commands.
The point is that it's token dense.
You know, a single token will list some files.
3 or 4 tokens will conduct a search and get the results.
So it's an extremely efficient way for a model
to to bring context into itself for further action.
And the other kind of the quite interesting thing here
is, is that we can seed models, you know, it's not just documentation,
but we can also provide
ready made or customizable scripts so that we can do some fairly big,
determined deterministic actions or modify those
actions fairly easily to,
to, to effectively extend,
massively extend the capabilities that we have.
So when one of the kind of things
that particularly interests interests us is
training and fine tuning
and deploying models, right. So,
so the general processes is that you have to
identify a data set that you want to maybe fine tune a model on.
So I'm hoping most people are familiar with fine tuning.
So the idea is that we would take an existing model.
We would then sort of get some data
which told us how we wanted the model to behave in future turns.
So we might, for example, a silly example would be a talk
like a pirate set of conversation pairs, and then we take the model,
and then we run the model through through a number of loops
where we where we say this is what we want it to look like.
And then ultimately a new model comes out the end.
You can download it and you can run it in a tool like llama
or LM studio or so on and so forth.
And this, you know, I would say up until we kind of had these skills,
this wasn't something that was necessarily casually accessible.
Okay.
So what the skills enabled us to do was to and again, using straightforward
off the shelf tools like Claude code, we can say add this skill and it will
then guide you through the process of constructing a data set building.
You know,
do you want to synthesize your own data or do you want to use someone else's data?
What hardware do you need to actually do this?
In fact, again, you might be surprised.
You know, often it's sort or $3 worth of worth of
compute to do some very, very basic fine tunes.
But it will run the training scripts, it will set up,
it will set up monitoring for you so you can watch the loss curves.
It will turn it into a goof format so that you can run it locally.
And so,
you know, skills have kind of made this a huge amount
more accessible for people to actually start to think, right?
Well, you know, even in fairly simple cases, it's become very accessible
to build and tune and fine tuning the local model.
We've then also got
some slightly more sophisticated, sophisticated needs.
So we were just talking about kernel writing.
I'm certainly not an expert, but for the people that are again,
we've got,
you know, a kernel library, kernels is now something that we host on the hub.
And the idea behind hosting kernels on the on our hugging face hub like this
is because there is still, as we saw from previous talk,
there are still optimizations that people can make
and have for particular hardware classes, for particular particular algorithms.
And so kernel building and distribution is something that we can do.
And also the nice thing about that is that certainly for kernels
we can actually have a fairly deterministic outcome as to did it work
and was it faster or more efficient than the previous one before.
So again, a quite a useful, quite a useful thing for us.
It was there just I've put a note
on the slide I did want to mention this is that
obviously we maintain a number of quite important libraries
like kernels, like transformers, like diffusers, which people use to
to build and testing, train and deploy their own models.
And so rather than what we've generally found is that we're finding it
more valuable for people to, for example, download kernels
or transformers and then add the skills through their own CLI.
So you can say transformers add skill to the local directory
rather than having some other third party installer.
It feels a lot more comfortable to package it to package it that way.
So the so when it comes to does this stuff, does this stuff actually work?
I'm just going to pop to a pop up and slide in a moment.
Was it's all that we built and we're still maintaining.
We like it quite a lot is a tool called upskill so that we could
we could do a number of
things actually, so we can look at existing traces
or existing skills and generate new skills.
We can evaluate whether or not the skill is actually useful,
or we can compare the performance
of one skill against another skill for a particular task.
Or and again, we kind of did this with the kernels.
We can use large models to generate instructions that we can
then use with smaller models so that we can get similar performance
from smaller models.
So it's almost like a very kind of crude form of distillation,
if you like, where we are, where we have a big model due to smaller models,
which may be faster, cheaper or a better fit for any number of reasons,
and the kind of things that we that we see that this is.
I didn't include this in the presentation, but,
you know, this is a this is a kind of example.
One of the things that
building the
MCP server and developing these skills is important for us
is making sure that what we're building is applicable and working across
a wide range of open weights and proprietary frontier models.
And sometimes we have to make trade offs where we may
see a drop in performance in one model, but it improves other models.
So it's always a slightly shifting thing.
But again, in this example, I think this was quite
a fairly outrageous one where we've got two versions of the skill
and it generally the improved version of the skill generally improves
performance quite a lot, except for grok four,
which for some reason goes through the floor.
But, you know, it's always a very, very strange model.
And so the other nice thing that we can do with upskill is,
you know, it's when when we first developed this,
we were doing quite a lot of local development
and all of the kind of tropes and memes about agents running
wild came true as we were developing upskill and kind of running,
running tasks like right
Cuda kernels or finish off a good pull request as models were sort of running
over each other and stealing each other's results and generally misbehaving.
But so what?
Skill does now.
In fact, I'm going to why don't I?
I'll be brave enough to live demo.
But again it's you know, a typical upskill run might be something where we
where we write, integrate and benchmark and optimize Cuda kernel
and we can see that it does improve performance.
So based on the automated tests it produce, it improves performance.
But obviously the expense of rather more tokens okay.
But these are the kind of
things that we that we like to know and we like to kind of calculate.
So I'm just going to I think that will run.
So this, this upskill, I've got a
I've taken our normal kernel skill.
It's now generating some test cases.
We're not going to see this to completion, but I just kind of
want to just kind of show how it integrated with a couple,
of a couple of other components.
But, you know, we can give it a skill file, we can tell it which models we want
to use for generation, for evaluation, for testing or for benchmarking.
And we'll see if this then
submits any jobs.
So I cancel some jobs earlier.
We'll let that run the other.
And of course the other nice thing is that we've been spending quite a lot of time
working to collect and make it easy to publish agent traces.
So the idea being that we can,
given given an agent run is easy for you
from your harness, whether you're using, in this case, fast agent.
In other cases, it could be Pi or Codex or Claude.
It makes it easy to publish and share those traces so that you can
then have a really good a really good look at what actually happened
and where the tool calls were and where there were any errors
and that kind of stuff.
So if you.
So after you've run upskill, I'm good.
I'm not going to obviously get those jobs running.
Oh there it goes.
So yeah.
So it's now created a sandbox for each of those particular evals.
They should appear with scheduling in a second.
I'm determined to wait for it
now, so I'll try and crack some jokes to keep you entertained.
Yeah.
There it goes. Look at that. Sorry.
Oh, yeah, that one's.
Well, that one's doing some analysis on pull requests for transformers,
so you can see they're all nicely labeled.
Our jobs are now all running.
So each has got a very isolated sandbox.
It's not going to mess up your own local computer.
And of course in cases where you have things like a kernel performance test,
you can actually deploy it on some sort of decent hardware.
This is running on CPU basic at the moment, but we could
we could run that on some on some fairly serious harbor if we needed.
So so the nice thing about skills is,
you know, it's, it's it kind of almost
when we're using it for tutoring installation, best price performance.
It kind of gives us something between the hassle of fine tuning something.
It's a lot simpler than that,
but also something which gives us a huge amount of extra boost
so that we can use better fit models for for a particular task.
The other kind of thing, just just an area
where I think we're going to start to see some real progress very soon.
So I'd say this is
some of the stuff I'm talking about is probably a slight work in progress,
but I think this is something which is quite important for us is
we we're kind of increasingly seeing that
the people
like interacting with things in a fairly natural language.
And we've got a fairly
we haven't got a huge API surface, but it's a big enough API surface
that it can be sort of somewhat difficult to navigate and manage otherwise.
And so we want to give people sort of, you know, fairly good and free
free access to that.
And of course, models are very, very good at generating codes and scripts.
I'm mentioning the tool builder there, which is a, which
is actually another skill that we have which will navigate our open
API spec and build shell scripts or Python scripts that you can compose together.
But the other thing that we we started doing is
some code, some code generation.
So we've got a general query tool.
And the reason I kind of bring this up
is because one of the important things about this query tool
is that it generates code, and then it doesn't post-process the result.
It gives you the answer straight away.
And we're using in this case at the moment we're using GPT 120 B,
which is a it's it's a reasonably model, but it's very, very fast.
Right.
So one of the things that we're keen to do is to reduce latency as much as possible
and to use the right model for the job, but again, you can.
So what proportion of training models have a number in their name?
Okay. That's that's a query.
You may not ask very often but it's not an unreasonable query.
And again
you can see how quickly that code generates and actually returns an answer.
Now of course, you know, we can think of
how many followers does the invisible organization have.
So again, you can kind of get this extremely snappy performance.
And we expose this as an CP tool.
At the moment there's some further tuning to do, but
given a kind of set of traces, given a set of inputs
and what we then know with good outputs, we can start to think, right?
Well, actually we can we can start to evaluate
what good looks like over a fairly large set of data.
And we can then start to think about having an even smaller model
and even faster model, and a better way of actually doing those things together.
And we can extend that even further because something that again,
we're we're starting to see,
I'm not not entirely sure how this is going to fully work for us yet,
but the idea that we can actually generate UI on the fly, right.
So a model which knows how to generate UX components to answer certain questions,
show proportions, show particular information, starts
to become a lot more feasible.
Right?
Because, you know, if we're able to customize and train and specialize
models for these particular tasks, then we're in a position where we can
they can be cost effective and fast enough for this to work well. So
again, you know, afterwards
are more than happy to talk about this because I've done an awful lot.
Some we haven't covered here is MCP tool description of valuation,
which I know is kind of like a big thing a few months back.
And certainly we've looked at and we continuing to look at how we want,
how we can avoid confusion in the model when it's given multiple options.
But ultimately, the great thing is that we're
now in a position where models can train other models, right?
Models can use other models sensibly, they can train other models sensibly.
We've now got self-improvement.
It's here if you want it.
Owning and usefully customizing your own models is completely accessible.
Try it if you haven't already tried it, give it a go.
You might have to.
You might have to copy and paste a few error messages in and have the have them
sort it out.
You may have to, but you will get it working
very a lot more quickly than you think.
You can train a model to recognize your pets a lot more quickly
than you think.
This stuff is very, very accessible.
Frontier models are overused, right?
The price performance of big models like opus
or GPT five five is is not as expensive.
We throw all kinds of trivial problems at them all the time.
We shouldn't we should not do that.
It's a waste of compute.
It's a waste of money. It's a waste of tokens.
It's a waste of water.
It's something that we kind of need to start getting used to
because we we've got techniques and very, very simple tools
that get us to exactly where we need to be with price performance.
Open weight models are yours.
You can adjust them, you can run them, you can.
You can do as you need with them.
You're not beholden to other people making decisions
arbitrarily on what is allowed on an API or anything else.
Right? You take ownership of this stuff.
And finally, inference and execution is blending,
as I kind of mentioned, with the harnesses,
you know, we've kind of seen complex harnesses start to collapse
towards being model enablers.
And as we kind of see more advanced APIs like the responses
API or you do more local running, actually the difference
between inference and execution environments is starting to blend, right?
They're starting to become one of the same thing.
So anyway, I'm around afterwards if anyone wants to talk about any of these topics.
I hope that was
useful in some way.
And thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Sean.
Any questions?
Good talk sir.
Thanks very much.
I'm curious, since you're so well plugged into this space,
one of the areas of self-improvement comes up a lot of times is low
resource programing languages, things which are less popular.
I'm curious if that's crossed your radar.
Where do you see people put this to use of an ecosystem
that isn't as big as Python or JavaScript, and getting good results?
I can't think of anything directly at the moment,
but I definitely agree
that that is is a very ripe area where, you know, we
I mean,
I know that people have certainly done quite a lot of experiments of fine
tuning on particular code bases, and they generally tend to find it's worth it
when they do it.
But it's a maintenance has probably not got the payback for small teams.
But yeah, I think it's something that
something that's
right for ripe for exploitation.
Great job with so much information.
I don't know where to start, but I think you pointed out
to a lot of things that show that when compared to 12 to 18 months,
which is one of your slides, we need to have all of these tools.
And now, let's say 18 months from now, if you had to give the same talk,
of course will be a different discussion.
But when you see things going like we've already progressed so much,
like the developer tooling space has become so powerful, where do you think?
And also you pointed out something else is there.
The harnesses and tools are getting lighter
and it's getting factored into the models, right?
Sean, sorry about this earlier.
So where do you see things happening?
Is going to be doing just pushing buttons and.
Maybe I think
this might be a slightly cynical take.
I think over the next 12 to 18 months, what we really need
to see is real usage and deployment of these models
to solve problems that aren't deploying and using models, right.
So a huge amount of the explosion of software
we have at the moment is all based around, you know, literally
what we just spoke about, which is can I do inference, can I?
Right at all.
Can I do all of these things?
And we kind of keep on extracting this training data
out of the models and then sort of going, it's fantastic.
We I think what we're going to, you know,
certainly what we should start seeing over the next 12 to 18 months
is more of a focus on deploying these for use cases, deploying models,
deploying these solutions for use cases, which are more generally useful than
building the tools to build the tools, if you know what I mean. Yeah.
So it's kind of like, you know,
we're we're very good at the building, the picks and shovels.
And it's a we need to we need to, we need to start using them.
And I think we've got to, we've got to a capability level
with current models that we there shouldn't be anything which holds us back.
So I think I think I would certainly hope in 12 to 18 months time we're looking at
clever.
Clever business
and societal application of some of these technologies.
I don't think we're getting the full value from.
I think there's a lot of potential and unrealized value
that I look forward to this concentrating on getting.
Thank you. Hi.
I'm there, and thank you so much for your talk.
So one use case
that I'm following right now is processing a large amount of individual.
And I'm using frontier models.
And I saw somewhere that you can use like alma for easy one.
Yeah. We wanted to quit operating it.
I was thinking about
like how much it will cost and how long it was going to take.
And basically I got the answer that you can do it for ten minutes,
like very small one.
So the two part of these questions, one is that
I did not go into this because I was not sure what kind of I'm going to get
or how am I even going to evaluate whether my results are really good.
So events are probably like a judge or something else would be an answer.
So that is what I want to know.
How would you compare this, these kind of results.
And second one is that if I have a use case like this.
So I always wonder that let's say a new model came up and they will have much,
much higher capability.
Yeah.
So if I'm only like 20,
my own open source model
and it will take some time to catch up with that,
and I might have to change my training of that.
So in case like that, how do you think about training
your basically
like fine tuning your own model versus just going with the frontier. And
so I mean, I would
probably kind of collapse the question almost into a cost benefit question.
Right?
Which is that, you know, it's
I think it's fairly straightforward to assert that a particular volume,
the cost of using a frontier model
is for the performance you get
is going to outweigh the effort and money
that you may need to spend to do some fine tuning.
How exactly you quantify that, I think, comes down to a lot of
whether you're doing it for personal fun, whether it's whether you've got
10 million data samples, whether you've got 500 data samples.
So I think it's a.
I think there's a lot of a lot of questions
to answer there, because obviously the more scale you have,
the more that trade off window comes towards that.
You know, a certain level of fine tuning or self hosting or
doing your own evaluations makes sense.
What I would argue, though, is certainly the
where the volume sided equation is pushing
you towards higher volume is going to mean, you know, the more volume you do,
the more it's going to be worth customizing and fine tuning.
But that the other side of the equation is also getting closer, which is it
is becoming a lot simpler to do that and running evaluations and so on.
So it's becoming cheaper to do it.
So I think, you know, for to be honest, I think for a lot of cases,
you know, we're probably not at that crossover point.
I think you would probably need to sit down with a spreadsheet
or Claude code or something and kind of figure it out.
But I think again, I would I would say, if you've got something
that's working for your use case, I and it's an important use case for you,
then I certainly think
that open weight models that you could potentially host yourself,
even if you're not hosting it yourself, would be something I would want
to keep hold of.
So I think there's other risks
that you, that you, that you, that you mitigate
by taking some ownership of the infrastructure.
Also, we don't have any more time for questions, but please give it up first.